[Music]
you're listening to the AI native Dev
brought to you by
[Music]
Tesla hello again and welcome back to
part two of this episode joining me is
Omar rosenal who is the CTO and founder
of swim and om we just had a a wonderful
discussion really about how AI can make
a really strong impact into a really
important problem around documentation
in a number of different ways first of
all how the awareness uh of the fact
that documentation even exists or how
it's connected and relevant to code a
developer is intending to change or
wanting to learn from that that
awareness is absolutely CA
and then secondly making sure that
changes to that code are kept in sync so
that there is no drift between code and
documentation a number of other topics
that we talked about but for me those
are some of the core areas that I guess
pay a developer so much today and we're
g to we're going to walk through that a
little bit in in this session so we're
going to jump into some screen shares
and you can show us that now you're
obviously going to be showing this using
swimm as the example but we're going to
be really talking through a lot of the
problems and how that can really be
helped with AI give us a brief intro
into swim for those who who perhaps
missed the first episode or maybe need a
refresher tell us a little bit about
swim sure so at swim we help
organizations understand their own code
by relying on static analysis
capabilities as well as generative AI we
help with generating documentation
automatically finding it when you need
it most and keeping it up to date as the
code changes to avoid drift amazing and
let's jump straight into the into the
screen share in fact I'll bring your
I'll bring your screen up here
um like to start from the end from when
you actually do have documentation and
get us all into the mind of a developer
who is trying to introduce a change to a
codebase that they don't know and
specifically I chose the code base of
git I really like git I also wrote a
book about git so I know some of the
code but we'll talk as if someone were
to introduce their first for request to
get source code and specifically to add
a new command to git CLI so like you
have git add and git commit and so on so
maybe you want to add get something else
and you're looking I'll be honest I
haven't done C coding for 20 years since
I was at University so I really need
some documentation to understand this
fair enough most people need to
understand need need some help to
understand new code they see right we
tend to forget it when we get acquainted
with the code base how hunting it might
seem at first glance so here if we
consider my workflow as a developer I
don't think about documentation I read
the code first right and I did some
searching and I found that there is this
file G.C which parses some things I
don't really understand it all the way
and at some point I get to this part
with a struct called CMD struct and I
see the wave icon here now this wave
icon tells me that someone has written a
document this someone could be a human
or AI someone has written a document and
mentioned this part of the code and
specifically if I hover here I can see
that it says that to make it aware of
the command it needs to be registered by
adding it and I see here that it's part
of a document titled adding a command if
I click on it it would open the document
on the right hand side now the important
thing to notice here is that I found the
document without searching for it right
I was browsing through the code and then
I saw hey someone documented this when I
clicked it opened up the document I'll
zoom out a bit so we can easily see but
this nippet here is actually those lines
from the
code so let me explain a bit how swim
documents look like so swim documents
consist of text and also three main
elements that are coupled to codebase
one is a snippet so you can see this
file sorry this document walks you
through multiple files it talks about
how you add a command and it says that
when you add a new command you have to
create a new file under the my built-in
folder and you need to update built-in.
Ag and also g. C if you click on one of
those Snippets it would also take you to
the right part in the
code so you can see what I'm talking
about here so a snippet is a few lines
of code from somewhere within the
repository another element is a token a
token is a part of a line for example
add here is not just the string ad it's
the token ad from line 485 this one
here third is a path like a name of a
file it could also be a name of a folder
Now by tracking and coupling we achieve
a few things one is that as a reader of
the documentation if I read this and I
try to understand what you're talking
about when you say add and I click it
shows me where it is if I click here it
will take me to the right place in the
code so it's easier to write or
understand what this is about and
another big Advantage we get is that we
can keep this up to date because we know
what part of the code we documented here
so for example say now I'm a developer
and I'm changing something here and
maybe I changed the name of this track
maybe I added a comment here so the line
number would change so some comment and
maybe I change here from commands to my
commands and I click on Save here if I
go back here to the document within
swim I would see that it shows me that
the code changed and it showed me the
before and after so it say hey look what
used to be commands in line 484 is now
my commands on line
486 and also the snippet changed right
commands turn to my command so this
changed and these kind of changes we
call a syncable that is we automatically
sync them with code and you can
configure swim to automatically click on
accept here and accept that as this is
now the source of truth because it's a
subtle change we might find this change
and you would want to add some
information I add another flag say the
tessel
flag here and now you might want to
explain that this flag is useful for
some cases where you want to add it so I
show you that this is the part that
actually changed and now you might want
to add this to the documentation and say
okay notice the you
of Tesla flag here and explain why we do
that notice that now this is not linked
to code but you see this dashed
underline that tells me oh you probably
wanted Tesla flag from this line right
yes now it's coupled to the code base
and from now on I would know that this
is the tesle flag I'm talking about and
of course I'll make sure it remains up
to dat the code evolves yeah when you
change the code
there are two ways to know it affects
documentation you can either add a git
hook that would tell you something is
outdated and then within the swim plugin
you can see what which doc is
outdated you can also see from the Icon
as before that here there is some
document it doesn't appear now because
it's outdated but before that you see
that there is an icon telling you
something there is some document that
corresponds to this code so if you
change it you don't need to check it
and as we mentioned before we also
integrate to the CI and the pr process
so if we look at the same codebase in
GitHub now and say I introduced a change
within
GitHub this
change made one document outdated so it
says there are docs that need your
attention this swim Dock and there is
also a check that fails because not all
documents are up to date if I click here
I go to swims web applic
which looks similar to what we saw in
the ID but it's from the web application
and I see here the elements that need my
attention so one is this so you see here
what used to be G.C is is now main.c so
in this P request I actually renamed the
file and I also changed it from commands
to sub commands and I could accept and
also it's this a very similar experience
to what you have in the IDE but you get
it from the web applic application as
part of your PO request process and now
if you want to add something as before
explained you can do it here it's also
editable click accept and at the end you
would commit it to the codebase all of
the documents or mckone files are stored
in the codebase by the way alongside the
code yeah so if we go back to the IDE
just for a second I think I think
there's a few workflows here that are
really interesting so the first one that
kind of struck me is before made changes
there and the and the the icon was there
it really allows me as a there it is
that kind of an icon it really for a
developer who is looking at this
codebase from scratch it's really nice
to be able to get that information to
say here is something that can actually
help you not just understand the code
but if you were thinking about the
workflows and how to change that code it
gives you that greater understanding
into that but I think when if a
developer is coming in here with the
intention
to make changes to code it's super super
important that they recognize these as
areas points at which there could be
drift and it highlights the fact that
okay not only should you potentially
read this if you are unfamiliar with
this code so that you know how to better
make that change but to safeguard future
developers and users uh of this code
make sure you document any code changes
so that they see that that up to date
version of this documentation I think
that first piece is super super valuable
which avoids that drift like we
mentioned in that first episode so now I
can see why as you said most swim users
prefer to do it in the IDE because it's
almost like they're almost like
validating the changes that are
occurring and I think it's almost that
much nicer to be able to do it as you go
and accept in the IDE that's I think you
mentioned that's the way that most of
your users users doation correct most of
them and I think also when they find
documentation that helps them when they
need it most that's also like a wow
effect right and extreme Cas is like
someone wrote here why they made the
change and then you read it and you're
like oh my God I was supposed I was just
going to change this and apparently it
had been done like so in the past but
someone fixed it and he explains here
why it's not a good idea and it's having
me so much time right then you got a wow
effect that you only get if you find
documents when you need them right no
absolutely just to add to what you said
before also the fact that we can put
this icon
here stems from the fact we keep this
link up to date otherwise you would see
an icon on the wrong snippet or on
something that is outdated right and
then it's more harmful than anything
yeah yeah so as you H how do you connect
this version of code to the the version
of the documentation in in swim do you
have a similar kind of git style
connection so if I was perhaps to get a
different a different branch or a
different version of the same code base
how do you keep that aligned right so
since the swim document are markdowns
stored within the repository in a folder
called sswm then they are also version
sourc version controlled like the rest
of the code so if I they change this I
commit and now when you check out this
commit or Branch you will see the
corresponding version of the code in the
document cool and what one of the one of
the things that when you go across into
the onto the plugin on the right hand
side I guess there are two pieces here
which is very interesting the first
piece which is a suggestion of what what
should be changed and then the second
piece which is I want to add some text
myself to guide effectively and provide
a snippet of code with a snippet of my
my my thoughts to to generate that
information I guess the first question
is without the guidance how good is AI
and I guess you use an amount of static
analysis on the code as well to
understand the flows how good are the
suggestions without any information
whereby if we were only to rely on that
would it be right like 70% of the time
80% so without any additional
context that you provide to AI it would
be 80% not what you want oh really wow
okay and only when you provide
additional context is it able to produce
something meaningful otherwise it could
make a lot of guesses that are
uneducated because we didn't provide it
with the right context when we provide
the right context it does a pretty good
job on it I think 80% of the time is
fair yeah but I think this also back the
question of how you get to write these
documents in the first place right and
where I think AI also shines so I'll
show that in a moment too yeah and that
shows how much is still of the context
is in the author of the developer's head
when they're making those changes to to
actually get it accurate that's super
interesting so it's it's a it's still a
very much an assistant style usage
workflow and the value for for the pr as
we mentioned in the previous session as
well is that of course you can have many
contributors into a project and some you
can't force a developer to use in this
case swim in their IDE they might just
go ahead and make changes and push push
some commits up and send a poll request
so it allows that that policy effect
across your entire project to make make
sure it isn't just two of your 10
developers that are writing code with
documentation changes and actually 80%
of the team are allowing the
documentation to go stale it allows you
to enforce your the parity between your
documentation and your and your
code definitely yeah okay cool yeah we
interestingly we looked at the swim
documentation here how's that I'm
curious how's that evolved over time has
it always looked like this or were there
were there various stages of learning in
terms of how you got to this this there
are there were many stages of
learning even didn't start as a markdown
file it started as a Json file that was
hard to read and know it evolved and was
refactored many times so that the
markdown can actually also be rendered
without using swim you don't get this
experience of clicking and getting to
the right file or all of the niceties
that you get from this editor but
everything is rendered just fine on says
code preview or github's preview yeah
okay cool and if you had existing
documentation how would you connect that
how would you couple that to the code so
you could import it into swim and since
it's marked down it's it actually works
out of the box but then you would go
over it and add references to the code
if you remember from before when we had
some things that are not coupled like
here this T here it tells me hey did you
actually mean this T maybe here so this
might be a silly example with just a
letter right but if it were a name of a
file or a variable from the code or
something like that we would say you
probably want to couple it here so we
make those suggestions for you so I
think now would be interesting to see
how you go about creating these kind of
documents I wanted to show two almost
extreme cases one is where I'm going to
guide AI into writing a document in a
way that I want it to be and the other
would be we'll look at a code base that
I don't know and for at least for the
sake of the story no one knows it's a
cobal repo it's a very big Cobo
repository that's open source and how we
generate documentation for this
automatically starting from the more
guided approach let's say I want to
create the same document as I did here
and I would start by going let's even
get it back to the original
state I'll start by creating a document
now when you think about creating a
document most people Envision like a
blank page something like this right and
let's write something which is a very
done state for most people I don't like
a blank screen most people don't so
instead what I want to do is to focus on
the code the code which in this case I
know because I want to document it and I
want to show how I create a new git
command so I just say okay if I were to
explain to Simon how I add a new git
command I would start by showing him
this truct so I'll select it right click
and swim add to new Doc this adds it to
a new document that would be created
here
and this creates that connection as well
so this is coupling the code to that doc
immediately correct and now you would
also see this icon here once I write
something in here correct so there one
then I can go to definition and do
anything that I would like let's say I
want to go to built-in. AG let's say
I'll explain about annotate this time
another commands so add to current doc
it would add this snippet now I'd also
go to where it's implemented so I go to
annotate doc
and I'll add
that add to corent Doc cool so now I
have three Snippets and let's say that's
the code flow that I want to say or in
this case the recurring pattern I want
to say generate draft with AI so I'm
going to give it a title how to add a
new command in git and here I can add
instructions if I want to in this case I
want to say explain how to add a new
command using
annotate as an
example and structure let's say
introduction the process adding a new
command what I want to get
now and as you'll see in a moment is an
educated version of a document that did
most of the heavy LIF thing for me in
terms of actually writing the text
explaining what does and also cing it to
code so you see for example here it says
declare the command function next with
declare the command function built-in.
AG it includes this element this
coupling to the code implement the
comment logic and so on and it needs to
be according to my instructions right so
if I don't like it I could revert and
add it prompt now there might be
something that I want to add that notice
that maybe in this version We do things
differently because such and such
everything here is editable right I
could go here now and edit it as I like
I can also select this and tell AI hey
make it shorter make it better make it
different so I can use AI but at some
point I think when we want to extract
our own knowledge I'm guiding AI by this
is the flow I want you to explain these
are the Snippets I want you to relate to
this is some general structure of the
document generate what you can and I'll
add my unique knowledge on top of that
and that would be a great document yeah
so what are the gaps here still then is
there still an is there a Gap
whereby the developer needs to initiate
this process I'm trying to I'm trying to
work out what the of course yeah of
course this specific process assumes two
things one you know the code and two you
decided to document it right yeah and I
guess for some cases this is the perfect
answer for me I use this a lot I
implemented something and I want to
share the know about it with the rest of
the team this is much easier for me than
anything that is super automatic because
I can guide it exactly as I want if I
were new to a code Bas it doesn't really
help me as much and I'll show how we
approach that afterwards so the
developer needs to understand and this
is almost like a developer training
other developers in the team or people
who are completely outside of the team
and unfamiliar with with how to do this
how it should be done but it massively
speeds up the process of that and
actually then can actually pinpoint and
relate to pieces of code
so that people can click through and
actually see in their IDE what to do but
I think then linking that then back to
what we previously discussed as things
change this keeps up to date which which
is what makes this relevant not just the
day it was created but later that
afternoon and in the future as well
which is exactly and then you can you
can also find it in the ad when you need
it yeah so makes sense to write it and
also it's much easier because
essentially I just selected the right
snippet set a few instructions and I
have a document right yeah so this is
the approach that we take when you do
know the code I want to get it what
happens when you don't looking at
another
repository that I'm going to bring in
now this is a cobble repository called
Kell you can find it on GitHub and to
generate documents for it so a user
would click on generate and then there
is some analysis that happens once we
perform the static analysis understand
all the relationships in the codebase
and then the first thing we do is
suggest a list of modules that we think
the documentation should be structured
according to so these are modules that
we found in the repository they could
correspond to a single folder maybe to
some folders in files it's some logical
component and this is generated by us or
is this suggested by the AI suggested by
swim by
sistic version with AI helps refining
the names here
but finding and separating the different
components is done deterministically and
we have a few different tics so if you
don't like this you can res suggest you
get another
suggestion and then if you don't know
the code at all you would probably pick
one and say next and just generate
everything for me but if you do know the
code and you click next we tell you okay
we think now the VIP section should
actually be separated into reports
transactions management you can say no
you know what I don't want transactions
but maybe I want something else and add
to it so you can change what the
structure looks like then when you click
on generate we generate it could be
dozens hundreds or thousands of
documents depending on the size of the
repository starting with this document
here the overview document which
basically in this case I took the first
suggestion that we saw before so this
one and the overview document explains
what this repo is about what the
interactions are between the different
components and then for each component
okay what is it about in general a
paragraph and a few links to other
documents we generated about this which
could be an overview of this logical
component and it could be a full flow so
this is the main document and again if
we're talking about a CIS nobody knows I
think anyone who gets into any task
would appreciate a high level overview
yeah then let's say I know I want to
change something specific in a specific
place we can look so this is cobal so to
those of you who haven't had the
pleasure of programming cobal reading
cobal code is mainly split into programs
so this is a type of a document we have
only for cobal it doesn't really make
sense to document a Python program what
is a Python program right and coob it
does so we also document a program and
we explain the flow of the program so
this is what the program does
visually and this is a swim document the
diagram also keeps up to date by the way
because these elements are coupled to
code M and then we go step by step and
explain what every part does again you
click you get to the relevant part of
the code let me get some more space here
it remains up to date if you change the
code and everything we saw from before
just that this document was generated by
AI explaining the process of say this
program I guess the risk at this stage
is there's almost like an a far greater
reliance on the generation here being
accurate compared to that previous
instance whereby the developer
effectively knows that code in that case
it's going to be very hard and very
timec consuming for developers to
perform that validation effectively um
especially if they don't know the code
exactly yeah how much of a value versus
inefficiency of the documentation
potentially being wrong how much of a
balance is there in terms
ofs it's a good question first of all we
always have this disclaimer this is
autogenerated by swim AI hasn't been
verified by human and it's important to
note right it could be we take lots and
lots of precautions to writing things
that we're more confident about and
people who read this know it was
generated by AI know it's supposed to
help them we don't expect any
organization to go through all the
documents and validate them I don't
think it makes sense I think when a
developer or product manager talk about
that in a moment say a developer wants
to change some part of the code they
find the relevant documentation when
they look through the code as before
they read the documentation they see
that it helps them and if they want to
add or change something they do it on
the fight so it's not like a major
effort however of course if we on the
extreme if you generate documentation
that is all incorrect it could be just
misleading and harmful even so we put a
lot of effort
into getting the right context for AI
and then validating the output before
horor showing it to users yeah yeah so
I'm guessing that as a user of something
like this where it's a completely new
codebase it of course gives me an
amazing first step in in terms of
actually understanding the structure
very quickly I can then go to a relevant
part and then I guess as I look as I
want to learn more let's say I do want
to make a change to a legacy piece of
code because it's an urgent security or
critical bug change that I need to fix I
can at least start with that and then as
I actually start reading through the the
the the documentation the various
Snippets I'm I I can effectively
validate as I read the pieces I want but
it's important the developer to
recognize I need to validate this wasn't
written with a with another human uh
involved who knew this code so the the
validation almost occurs at two separate
points previously it was as the
documentation was being written here
it's probably more when that
documentation needs to be used in anger
because there's an issue that they need
to that they need to fix correct yeah
definitely and also as you as they
browse the code they can see those
Snippets of information right on top of
the code that tells something then
they're like okay so I read the code I
read the code now this is maybe a bit
more complex maybe I'll click here and
I'll find that the doc might be
helpful so this is indeed the process
now I mentioned before product managers
as we saw especially for large
organization sometimes you want to
change something in your legacy system
because it starts from a business need
and then some product manager needs to
decide what needs to change and they
need to talk with engineering and pretty
often it happens that no one knows where
this even exists in the code so what we
did for that we generate different
versions of the same document in this
example this is a document that is
mostly made for product managers
business people who want to understand
something in a very high level so it's
just described there are no code
Snippets here right this section is
responsible for evaluating and
critiquing different fields for example
can critic contracts album sequences and
more okay so if I want to change
something here I can tell the developer
you probably want to look here because I
understand what it does in the business
from business perspective if you click
here it would take you to the more
technical document it's the same flow
but this time we say okay this is the
name of this program and it call this
section and then it calls this section
and now we zoom into a part of the flow
we explain what each part does what
sections it calls and so on so I I think
when you have the knowledge about the
code base you can then reflect it in
different versions in different language
in different depth levels for different
personas and use cases yeah and and it's
interesting actually because this leads
us back to that original conversation
which I think we actually had in in in
part one of this episode which is the
the the importance to mix Ai and static
a static analysis piece to actually not
just describe but truly understand and
the flows and when I look at these
documents I see various kind of zoomed
out versions of an style graph whereby
you effectively under you effectively
map out the flows between methods calls
objects and whatever it is box them up
and then all of a sudden you get the
bigger workflows the bigger modules the
programs and so forth and all the way
through to the business side so this
isn't chat GPT just going this looks
like that so let's put it in a box
called this it's a true static analysis
at its core which is creating that as
model I'm guessing and that's that's how
these graphs are built out yes and then
we build a knowledge bottom up so in
terms of language such as Cobble where
you might have variable names that don't
mean much we look at all the usages us
as static analysis we try to understand
what this does here we might rely on llm
to give a textual description and then
we rely on that when we look at that
section that uses this variable yeah now
you talked about the process we started
with a way more llm based approach or an
agentic approach okay this is the code
tell us what you need and understand and
it just went we tried for a long time
with many iterations and it just found
flows that started in one place then
jump to another not understanding it's a
completely different flow and it's it's
a really hard task yeah to really
understand all code flows and then say
to explain or to rank them which ones
are the most important to document here
the overview document to generate that
you need to understand what's not
important to include here yeah which is
very hard task right yeah so you need to
map out everything then summarize to
Pieces then decide which ones are
important here there is some hierarchy
even like Bank transactions between
branch operations so to generate that
you really need this bottom up approach
and I think the combination of static
analysis with AI to generate a really
nice looking document in the end in
coherent English makes a lot of sense
yeah amazing this is super interesting
technology I'm sure listeners and
Watchers of the video here can see
already and probably already thinking
how they can actually apply this to
their existing code bases how would you
suggest people if people wanted to try
swim out what what's the best ways of
folks getting
started so we have a free tier but I
encourage everyone listening to this to
reach out to us we're happy to walk you
through and understand your specific use
cases if you working in an Enterprise we
really like to understand your specific
use case and make sure we generate
documents that adhere to your
conventions to what you find most
valuable right because you can generate
lots of different docs based on the same
knowledge of the
code so we really appreciate having
these conversations and generating
documents that are customized to your
repositories or organization needs MH
awesome and the website swim. with the
doum right correct s
wm. perfect amazing this has been very
insightful very interesting to to see it
in action and and yeah great to see the
workflows and how valuable they will be
in in sitting in existing developer
workflows certainly thanks very much om
for sharing your knowledge with us here
and and yeah thanks everyone for
listening to another episode and tuning
in see you next time thank you s
[Applause]
thanks for tuning in join us next time
on the AI native Dev brought to you by
tessla
[Music]